this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this episode of se radio is
brought to you by Braintree if you think
that your payment system exists solely
for the purpose of transferring money
from your customers wallet to yours
think again Braintree rethink payments
learn more at Braintree payments calm /
se radio I welcome everyone to the
software engineering radio my name is
Kim cutter I'm going to be hosting the
show today and today we've got a newer
Ford hello how are you yeah good so Neal
is director software architect and Mimi
Wrangler at the software company thought
works he has spoken at hundreds of
developer conferences Neal has a degree
in computer science from Georgia State
University specializing in languages and
compilers and a minor in mathematics
specializing in statistical analysis he
is an internationally recognized expert
on software development and delivery
especially NT in the intersection of
agile engineering techniques and
software architecture Neal has authored
magazines articles seven books and
Counting and dozens of video
presentations has topics include
software architecture continuous
delivery functional programming and you
can find out more about Neal Etta's
website Neal 4.com so welcome to the
show Neal thanks happy to be here so
I've got a bit of a lead in here from a
previous show it was Rebecca Parsons
with show number 236 did a show on
evolutionary architecture yes you know
writing a book about that subject right
now as we speak it's my eighth book yeah
awesome so we're going to be covering a
different topic today around the skills
in architectural and needs to be
successful I'm in order to be an
architect which is closely related to
buy two books ago
presentation patterns which is one of
the soft skills you need architect can
you briefly describe me or what your new
book is about and where people will be
able to find it the new book on
evolutionary architecture there's a
website called evolutionary architecture
calm which has updates on the conference
presentations and the articles that
we've written about the subject so far
we're in sort of first draft stage of
the book right now so we are very close
to being finished with it so I hope to
get it published sometime
certainly later this year and maybe as
early as a second quarter so in your own
words what is a software acti that's
interesting because one of the other
things that I do as part of my
professional world is I'm sort of the
mascot for all things software
architecture at O'Reilly the publisher
so I'm sort of their subject matter
expert on things software architecture
including conference co-chair for the
O'Reilly software architecture
conference which is coming up in New
York in April and one of the things that
the people that arrive a have been
trying to get me to do is define
software architecture and I keep
refusing to do so because I don't I
don't think it's possible to define it
because it's way too multifaceted like I
had a friend at one point put together a
mind map of all the responsibilities of
an enterprise architect and it's massive
all the things that architects end up
touching and so rather than try to
create you know a single definition what
we've tried to do is create sort of you
know almost like hashtags of
characteristics that architects face
every day and certainly it's all the
technical stuff that you would expect as
an architect but I think the thing that
blindsides most burgeoning architects or
we actually have a special category
called accidental architects who are
people on a project that are making
architectural decisions they just don't
have the title because if you look at
architecture as from a technical
standpoint as the decisions that have
long term implications then even on a
two-person project you're making those
kind of decisions you just don't have
the formal business card that says
architect on it but the thing that
really trips up brand-new burgeoning
architects and
little architects who finally realized
that the official role are all the soft
skills one of the things that blindsides
people is you know suddenly now you're
having to have written correspondence
with people who didn't skip all the
English classes to go hang out in the
computer lab and play with you know
computer simulations and that kind of
stuff so suddenly all of your written
interaction is held to a much higher
standard than it was before and that
trips a lot of people so for a while
I've had this metaphor of the arctic's
role as being this person that rides the
elevator of a tall building all day
architects seem to be jack of all trades
and master of none or few riding the
elevator to the basement where the
engineers work and up to the top floor
where the sea levels work and
translating one to the other is that how
you see the Arctic's wrong
well absolutely that that gets to that
that multifaceted aspect of architect
because as soon as you start trying to
put it down you'll realize it oh well
the architect has to do that as well no
they have to do that and in fact I think
that has gotten even more complex over
the last few years as we've really
delved into these kind of agilent's new
practices like a Tina's delivery because
of Lee now architects have to start
thinking about the DevOps implications
of the architectures they're designing
much earlier which at the end of the day
is a good thing because it gets a faster
feedback loop going between the
architecture and operations and what it
takes to actually operationalize an
architecture but it also means that an
architect's responsibility is broader
now because you have to start thinking
about things like DevOps some things
that used to be comfortably tucked away
in their own silo and of course we
realize that anytime you do that with
software you end up creating inadvertent
friction and so the best way to do
software is with really good tight
feedback loops so what do you think
about the idea are the architects are
born predisposed with a special set of
attributes I don't think that's
necessarily true although patience of
the saint
probably helps and the ability to sit in
meetings so if you were born with a
genetic defect that prevented you from
sitting in meetings you'd be miserable
as an architect because that's the thing
that
a lot of architects lied is they even up
it a lot of meetings that they never had
to go to before with you know business
type people with you know very less very
less interesting things than the kind of
technical meetings I have certainly
there's a leadership aspect to a
Software Architect and one of the things
that I think people miss is that really
effective software architects are good
speakers and presenters they're really
good at conveying their ideas to not
just technical people but also business
people but also don't think that's an
innate talent that's absolutely
something you could practice and so one
of the things that we strongly encourage
tech leads and burgeoning architects
with in Thal works to do it's do
presentations do brown-bag lunches do
presentations at conferences the more
practice you get at being able to
express yourself in high-pressure
situations the better you're going to
find yourself position to do that when
you become an architect what do you
think the top four skills required are
to be the best architect anyone can
possibly be
last year in preparation for the
O'Reilly so architecture conference I
actually wrote an article where we
interviewed a bunch of architects and
one of the questions we asked them or
what do you think the most important
characteristics an architect should have
and we've got a lot of really
interesting answers you get the normal
kind of things like you know
understanding technical having technical
acumen and understanding technical
issues but a lot of those came down to
soft skills being able to reach
compromise between disparate groups of
people who all have their own priorities
being able to really express an
architectural vision effectively to
business people and technology people
that's extremely important but another
thing I think that's really important so
this would be number three I guess is
understanding the nature of knowledge
itself in architecture here's what I
mean by that so as you are progressing
through your technical career what
you're trying to do is learn
more and more stuff deeply so what
you're working on is your technical debt
you're trying to become deeper
technically and learning more and more
very very specific things but when you
reach the role of architect it turns out
that debt is not as valuable as breath
because as an architect knowing that
there are five different frameworks
available that will allow you to
implement this multi-threaded scheduling
algorithm is better than knowing how to
implement that algorithm in a specific
framework like akka and so in some ways
architects have to shift the way they
think about things and start gradually
giving up some of the hard-won expertise
that they garnered and give it up in
exchange for getting more breadth and
that's always a painful thing for
technologists to do this give up and
give up on knowledge but it actually the
who's an architect to broaden their
technology rather than narrow it down to
the hyper specific sorts of things so
that's the third thing is understand
that when you become an architect the
way that you gather information and the
way that you think about things start
subtly shifting and so you said four
things here's the fourth one so one of
the things that we think about as
architects a lot are all these illa T's
all these architectural characteristics
that we're trying to assess in addition
to things like business requirements we
also have these external factors like
resiliency or scalability or security or
things like that
all these illa T's that we have to think
about but one of the the illah T's that
I don't think architects wield nearly
enough is feasibility and this gets back
to something I was talking about earlier
about the expanding role of architect
because one of the side effects of the
architect having a much broader role
inside organizations now is that they
have a much broader context on things
like should we even be trying to do this
and I think a lot of architects don't
pull the feasibility card quickly enough
to say you know what maybe this is not
such a good idea you know I know we say
that it's a really tight timeframe and
really ambitious scope and we'll try
really hard
but you know maybe that's not gonna work
and maybe we should think about
something else I think understanding
feasibility is one of the most powerful
illa T's is also a really good skill for
an architect to have yeah excellent
points so how do you deal with losing
your technical skill was due to
constantly being pushed up the ladder
like I personally have to deal with
quite a bit of frustration around this
and feel constantly torn between needing
to go deep on technical areas and in
losing focus of the bigger picture and
vice versa it's just an issue you face
and how do you deal with it oh yeah
everyone who becomes more seniors starts
lamenting the fact that they don't get
as much technical stuff under the belt
anymore and so there are two ways that
we've kind of grown to attack this
problem within thought works one of them
is to as the architect carve out some
stuff within the codebase to work on it
should be non-critical path stuff one of
the things that's really useful because
one of the things that you constantly
have to do as an architect is assess new
kinds of frameworks and tools to see how
well they work within your ecosystem
because you can read web pages about
things like what frameworks and message
keys but until you've tried them in your
real ecosystem you don't understand what
impact they will have and so doing those
kind of agile spike
exercises within your codebase to assess
new things to see how well they'll fit
within your ecosystem allows you to stay
in the codebase and and keep off of
anybody's critical path which is usually
a good combination for architects
because it get distracted so much but
the much better way I think to do this
is to pair with people on your team on a
really regular basis even if you're not
a company that regularly does pair
programming this has a lot of different
benefits one it allows the architect to
get in the codebase and see what's going
on at the ground level some this is also
a great way to get junior developers up
their skill level this is just like
playing with a tennis player that's
better than you it'll make you a better
tennis player same is true if your pair
programming with someone who is much
more experienced than you are because
you see problems come up in the context
of real codebase and see the thought
process of how they think about solving
them and what steps they go through to
solve themselves
a really great way to serve two purposes
one to get your hands in the codebase
and also to a skill level for some of
the people on the team or maybe it's not
even upskilling level but you're working
on a part of the codebase it's really
really difficult that would benefit from
having two brains working on it
maybe carve some of that time out to do
some peer programming as well so what
other ways do you use to attempt to
retain other skills that you want to
hang on to like are the skills and
talents that you feel that have been
taken away from you I think some of them
you just have to let go because you
can't hold everything in your head but
there are some things that you hold on
to just because they remain particular
passion as for one reason or another so
I'm one of the things that I'm holding
on to clutching on to for dear life is a
functional programming and particularly
closure I really like functional
programming and I love closure a lot and
so any sort of coding project that I do
on my for myself tends to be in closure
now and that's the only real I used to
be a real language geek and in fact one
of my books in being years ago was
comparing a bunch of different java web
frameworks so I love different languages
but I don't get a lot of time to dabble
in that now because I'm spending so much
time in the architecture space but I do
spend a little bit of time in closure
just because it's such a beautiful
elegant language so I think architects
find some things that they continue to
latch on to and still but it almost
becomes a hobby within your career of
the stuff that you just can't bear to
let go that's part of the job market X
is identifying ok which things can I not
bear to let go and which things can i
you know sail off to sea so what
techniques do you use to transfer
essential information amongst software
engineers in yourself and everyone else
other than adding more meetings which
you're often counterproductive I'm
thinking of things like peer pro gaming
it's been quite helpful there I mean
what other techniques do you have though
yeah peer programming is the best for
sure but and this is something that I
think we've always struggled with in
architectures coming up with any kind of
good specific Ain specification language
you know
they're kinds of engineering have come
up with ways of creating schematics and
other sorts of understandable things but
we struggled to do that in software I
don't think things like UML are
particularly useful for this because I
think and I've always had this theory
that UML is flawed because it's too
technical for non-technical people but
it's not technical enough for technical
people it's not really deep enough to
get really expressive for a technical
standpoint but it is technical enough so
that you can show it to business people
they don't understand it and so I've
been looking at as an alternative to
something like UML Simon Brown c4 model
Simon Brown is a really well-known
architect in the UK and he's come up
with this c4 model of doing capturing
software diagrams c4 stands for context
container component and class the
context being the larger business
context sort of what you'd normally
capture in something like a use case
about who the roles are acting and the
big moving parts the containers are the
physical partitioning of the system into
things like physical infrastructure
components are software components
either services or things like
components and in classes of course or
just classes I find that that's a more
useful way to capture a lot of that kind
of information because it's sort of
targeted toward different audiences
implicitly so the for example the
context diagram is sort of targeted for
less technical more business people who
just want the kind of bigger picture
whereas as you drill down deeper you get
into more and more details of how those
things look and work if Simon brands got
a bunch of them books on a lane pub tell
you which are quite good they are
and he's also open sourced a tool called
structure Iser for both dotnet and Java
that allows you to so you're asking so
this comes full circle you're asking how
do you stay in the codebase well
structure Iser is one way to do that
where you actually write Java or C sharp
code that generates all your software
architecture diagrams that's an open
source tool that you literally
instantiate you know classes and it
draws the thing for you so it seems like
a lot of work to me but if you're
absolutely desperate to do some coding
then it seems like a good way to and of
course generated diagrams are always
better than typically better than
hand-drawn ones I just I worry about the
overhead but ultimately the answer to
your question I think and we've found
this to be quite successful within
thought works is this idea of a
lightweight architecture decision record
this regained this is but this idea has
been around for a long time but it sort
of regained popularity recently when
Mike died guard of cognate echt released
a blog entry about how they're using
architecture decision records within
cognate Act and the idea is very
lightweight text based document that it
is expected to go in version control
right alongside the source code
typically in markdown or asciidoc or
some sort of text based markup language
and really what you're trying to capture
there is just the essence of why we made
this particular architectural decision
because the problem is you you're
presented with some sort of
architectural decision like okay we need
to add we have a current integration
architecture and we need to add external
business business integration and we
need to add website integration and we
have a message queues should we create a
hub to sit in between those guys and the
message queue or not so that's a typical
kind of architectural decision that
you'll be presented with and there are a
lot of things that you have to think
about as an architect to analyze to see
if that's going to make sense or not you
have to think about single point of
failure and scalability and what's the
purpose so you're going to go through
this analysis it seems with shame to
lose all that analysis once the
decisions made and you decide okay we're
going with a federated hub and that's
what you implement in code but then all
the analysis that went into that kind of
disappears that's really the goal of an
architecture decision record is to
capture that analysis in this light away
away as possible so it doesn't get lost
so part of an ADR record is the context
in which you're making the decision what
the decision is what the backing
supporting is supporting evidence is and
then perhaps what you think is a side
effect of this decision is going to be
in the near-term future and you can also
mark a status on 80 ARS
either proposed which means we're
thinking about this accepted which means
we're doing it or superseded which is
also important because sometimes you
make decisions for a perfectly
legitimate reason within an architecture
and then the whole ecosystem changes
underneath you and suddenly that's not
the appropriate decision anymore it
would be nice to still have the history
of why we made that decision initially
and then why we replace it later and so
you're trying to capture that in 80
hours as well I don't think it's perfect
it's way far from perfect and it's
nowhere nearly as good an engineering
artefact as other engineering
disciplines have but we're still working
on that we're a very young engineering
discipline compared to those others so
give us time we'll come up with better
stuff but that's the best thing that I
think we found so far so keeping things
simple is often really well often harder
than it sounds what do you think that is
it's interesting you say that because
this observation of mine that keeps
coming up over and over again is and I'm
actually putting together a talk for
this next year about stories every
architect should know I think one of the
things that is bad about software
architecture is that because there is so
much stuff to know we tend to always
look in the future at new cool stuff and
don't look in the past for really
important lessons learned on I'll just
give you one of these
pets.com so the origin of this talk was
I kept when I was doing these software
architecture fundamental training
courses I would ask people do you know
about pets.com and nobody knows about
these really important stories from the
past so pets.com is famous because
they're the first company that was so
successful it destroyed them so they
were I don't know if you remember pest
calm this may not have been an even
phenomenon outside the US but they were
the first they came out they were going
to be the Amazon of pet supplies and so
they came out with this massive
marketing campaign with big commercials
during sporting events and all that sort
of stuff
problem is they spent more money on
marketing than they did on actual
software infrastructure that so when
people were trying to place orders it
was crashing all the time they were
dropping orders and their reputation
became so bad
destroyed the company so they were the
first company that's so successful that
destroyed them so that's an example of
one of these stories but so one one part
of what I'm doing is I'm putting all
these stories together is looking for
the common theme or thread that kind of
runs through them and I think I found
what that is and it is the answer to
your question of why do things get so
complicated all the time and it's some
observation that I made a while ago but
I think it's still true and that is that
metalwork is more interesting than work
I don't know of a single developer who
wouldn't rather write a framework then
use a framework to create something
valuable for the business because
writing a framework is cool all these
complex problems will solve and all
these things that nobody's ever done
before so this is what I tell people is
like okay when you really boil it down
to its essence as a developer let's say
you're describing this your job to your
grandparents at the end of the day you
take things off webpages and put them in
databases take things off data out of
databases and put them on webpages yeah
there's a bunch of details in between
all that stuff but at the end of the day
that's kind of what you're doing and as
a developer if you've done that for you
know five or ten or fifteen different
projects it gets kind of dull so what
developers do when they get dull is
invent cool puzzles to solve and that
way they've got a cool puzzle to solve
every day when they come into work
that's the metal work is more
interesting than work and I'll give you
the perfect example of this that just
came up on one of our clients I was
chatting with one of our clients and
they were talking to the the
infrastructure team of developers and
they were currently in the process of
ripping out all the angular front-end
stuff and replacing it react and I said
so why are you guys doing that because I
mean you're getting everything you need
out of the angular stuff it's like well
we suspect that this is going to be
better in the future so we got a
two-year plan to replace all the angular
stuff with react so you know the Golden
Gate Bridge in San Francisco this famous
iconic bridge it's right there on the
ocean and one of the side effects of
that is there's a crew that paints the
Golden Gate Bridge and they start on one
end and it takes them a year to get to
the other end by the time they get to
the other end the original
and already has an assault damage so
they just start over so that's their job
is to perpetually paint the Golden Gate
Bridge that's what this team of
engineers is doing they're painting the
Golden Gate Bridge they're not adding a
business value they decided you know
what talking to business people is messy
and they're just gonna give us a bunch
of stuff we have to figure out and
problems to solve you know what if we
just play here in the infrastructure for
the next two years by the time we get
all the react stuff in there the next
big web frame won't gonna be along and
we could spend two years replacing that
and never actually have to worry about
talking with the messy business people
or anything like that and just keep
painting the Golden Gate Bridge so I
think that's why things get too
complicated is that meta work is more
interesting than work it's so hard to
get back to simplicity because we love
complicated little puzzles to solve and
so we keep over-engineering everything
toward the goal of well I'm sure we're
gonna need this or you know we keep
justifying all these reasons for over
complicating things when it's rare to
find them legitimate reasons I mean so
why is history so important and what
should we learn from it well we just
like any sort of scientific endeavor
people are gonna stumble and fall and
you know it's nice not have to stumble
and fall in the same way it's it's
important to understand a lot of these
lessons about you know about how to make
decisions about things so there's a
great book about this in fact one of the
stories is derived from this book called
dreaming and code by a Scott Rosenberg
you know this book it's an interesting
book because it's the story of the
software project that had infinite time
and infinite budget and it still failed
so all these software developers who
keep saying man I think we just didn't
have these budget constraints of these
time constraints we could build
wonderful stuff well this team didn't
have those constraints and they still
failed because they just kept building
framework after framework after
framework there was nobody there holding
their feet to the fire and saying are
you delivering value so that's one of
the things that we keep harping on
within vault works is is there value in
the thing that we're doing here value as
measured by business and
maybe there is business value of
stripping out old code for new web
framework because it does give you some
new capabilities like feature toggles
and the ability to a be testing or
something like that but we always try to
focus on is the real value in the thing
that we're doing here
not is it just some sort of interesting
puzzle that we're trying to solve so
some of the quotes you've mentioned on
your website such as those who cannot
remember the past are condemned to
repeat it and the pastor's never did
it's not even past strike a chord with
me how do we help our young engineers
understand the importance of learning
your history
well I'm trying next year I'm doing this
90 minute talk it's gonna be 12 stories
every architect should know and I mean
I'm actually thinking about writing it
down in book form because I think it's
it's interesting stuff you know it's
it's it's important lessons to learn
about things that you put together and
you know it seems a shame to have to
reinvent the same and you know have to
stumble across the same problems over
and over again and that's you know
eventually Sciences as they mature and
engineering practices they come up with
ways not to reinvent the wheel over and
over again
but we still have a real problem with
that there's a great quote and I can't
remember who to attribute this to I
believed his last name was cook but he
said we've been sold this idea that
software components were like swapping
out Legos but the reality is it's much
more like organ transplants and so I
think that's still true that we don't we
haven't quite figured out how to do this
software engineering stuff quite right
yet so can you discuss cleaver code
maybe with an anecdote in why you think
it's hard to maintain you know clever
code is is useful sometimes if it's
doing something of value again going
back to value but cleverness for the
sake of cleverness is not good and you
see this a lot actually I believe when
people are trying to embrace
multi-paradigm languages so good
examples of those or language like Ruby
or something like Scala in the Java
ecosystem because the problem when you
run into languages like that is
that you can do code procedurally you
can do it in an object oriented and ooh
it in some sort hybrid way and that sort
of encourages people to go down this
rabbit hole of whoo how clever can I
make this code particular language that
is as bendable as Scotland because you
got operator overloading you've got
first-class macros like a lisp so you
can literally rewrite pretty much any
part of language to do anything else you
want which is very clever but then it's
really hard for other people to
understand a great example of that I
think is at least the last time I looked
at it was the build tool that's common
in Scala the SBT the simple build tool I
think it's parenthetically I think it's
worth mentioning that anytime a tool
feels compelled to put the word simple
in the name of the tool it's probably
not it's probably marketing just like
the simple object access protocol soap I
wouldn't call that necessarily simple
but so anyway one of the things that
everybody knows about operator
overloading is that it's fine if you're
using it to implement something like a
vector or you can add two vectors
together and you can overload the plus
operator to marry two vectors together
but it's a bad idea to just invent new
operators out of whole cloth because you
eventually into recreating a language
like APL well if you look at SBT they
did exactly that
you know the bang equals greater than
sign Meade's do a make and the bang less
than you know percent sign means this
other thing which means that if you live
35 plus hours a week in Bill files and
you remember that language it's
beautiful and elegant and you can get a
massive amount of stuff done with almost
no effort if you only have to visit that
once a month it is absolutely
incomprehensible gibberish and anyone
who doesn't know all that context it's
going to be gibberish as well so I think
that's a danger that you get into in
multi-paradigm languages it actually
takes I think extreme team discipline to
make sure you stick with one paradigm
and don't create overly clever stuff
because developers love clever stuff I
mean that's part of
people get into software development
because it's puzzle solving and so
developers love clever stuff and it's
one of my old old quotes is developers
are drawn to complexity like moths to a
flame often with the same end result it
sounds a bit like regions are
expressions so eliminating complexity I
was discussed in the book that you were
involved with 97 things every software
architecture know how do we eliminate
complexity and do you have any other
examples well it's you know it's really
just focusing on what is the act the
real value that was the I was lucky in
that 97 things every Arctic should know
book because I was one of the first
people that he contacted so I got a nice
juicy one about essential versus
accidental complexity in there so that's
one of the things is understand what is
essential complexity versus accidental
complexity which is we just figured out
interesting ways to make it complex
versus it's just a really complex
problem to solve so for example genomic
analysis is just a complex problem solve
it has essential complexity but you
could make it a lot more complicated by
adding your own accidental complexity on
top of it and a great example of this is
essential versus accidental complexity
is one of the other stories from my 12
stories it's one that Dave Thomas who
co-wrote the pragmatic programmer book I
don't think he's actually written the
story anywhere but I heard him tell the
story and I got permission to to talk
about it and in my talk a long time ago
pride Dave and he's always called Prag
Dave by the way because there were two
Dave Thomas's that signed the agile
manifesto oti Dave Thomas and Prag Dave
Thomas so they're always distinguished
with that epithet to keep them apart so
Prag Dave Thomas back before he was a
publishing magnate was a consultant and
he was brought into this company because
they had a problem of routing internal
mail communications
paper-based communications because
things kept getting misrouted
and so then it would take a day for it
to get back to the message room and then
get rerouted back to the original
apartment so it was driving him crazy
and so they had figured out a way to
solve this problem with this real
elaborate and this is in the probably
late 1980s early 1990s so they had come
up with this optical character
recognition system who had read the
addresses and try to route at the
appropriate place and that brought Dave
in to help them write software to make
all this magic stuff happened and so
Dave said in meetings with them for a
couple of days and then he said when
they reached kind of a law he said you
know guys I'm sure you've probably
already thought of this and I feel kind
of silly for bringing it up but if you
thought about ever just switching to
colored envelopes and they sat around in
stunned silence and realize that you
know what if different departments had
different colored envelopes it'd be
super easy for humans to sort them and
they don't need this incredibly
elaborate optical character recognition
automatic routing all this stuff and so
they had contracted him for to write all
the software and they ended up giving
him a chunk of that money anyway because
he ended up saving them all the money
they were going to waste building this
thing because it seemed like a clever
puzzle to solve because he got to the
real essence of the problem the essence
the problem is Mis identification well
what mechanisms do you have to identify
things well there's color you're not
using that and that's a really easy
thing to use to distinguish things so
that's a great example of the kind of
simplicity that's obvious in hindsight
but it's really hard to come up with
with foresight but you know what when
you see it but it's really hard to come
up with it and so those architects I
think we should strive as much as we can
to try to find those kinds of things and
you know harbingers for those kinds of
can we radically simplify this and still
get the same result I think that's our
best battle against encroaching
complexity
[Music]
help us make se radio even better by
completing our short listener survey at
WWII Tripoli org / SC radio thanks so
what pills of wisdom do you have around
successfully bringing changes into an
organization or the teams within the
organizations we do this a lot actually
I'm a consultant so we get to see a lot
of transformation kinds of things within
organizations and tried lots of
different things over time and I've
gradually come up with a mantra I think
is the best way to attack these things
which is a demonstration defeats
discussion stop talking about how we're
going to transform the engineering
practices and DevOps or something like
that or start doing database migrations
you have to show them how that's going
to work and then you can have an
objective conversation about it because
as you as a developer you get really
excited about something like DevOps you
go to operations and say oh really
excited about this they're gonna say oh
no that's impossible here our system our
eco systems way too complicated to do
that with they'll find every reason in
the world to say no but if you could
show them even in a simple version of it
that hey this does actually work then
you could win them over a lot more
easily because you have a tremendous
inertia anytime you're trying to get a
transition to happen because what
happens is even if people are excited
about you know doing this new thing in
this new way and as soon as one
foot-pound if pressure is applied in
terms of schedule or anything like that
they instantly revert back to the old
way that they've done stuff because it's
just too hard to maintain a new way of
doing things while you know other stuff
is going on and so giving them room to
actually breathe and get used to it and
don't chicken out and show them that
it's actually going to be useful that's
one of the ways that you can convince
people that are skeptical is actually
demonstrate and so I've got a great
anecdote for that as well that comes
from Mike Nygaard when I mentioned
earlier it's really super well known in
the
the DevOps pace he was for a while the
de facto CTO this big box retailer and
he was trying to convince them that they
should do a lot more automation around
operations and DevOps and it was
essentially falling on deaf ears because
uh that's too complicated here we you
know our problem is way more complicated
than everyone else's we actually make a
joke within thought works at every
single company we go to at some point
says well you know our problem is way
more complicated than every other
companies
and of course it never is it's pretty
much always the same but let me finish
let me finish the Nygaard story before I
don't leave people hanging on that okay
this is part of the demonstration
defeats discussion idea and so he was
having a hard time selling this idea and
so he found a pain point this is a
technique that's known as consulting
judo because judo as a martial art uses
your opponent's weight against them and
so what he did was found a pervasive
problem within this ecosystem which is
they never had enough QA environments
they were always fighting over QA
environments and people try to share
them and they'd get conflicts and
overlaps and so he got an initiative
started to spin up programmatically QA
environments and that did two things one
it solved a real problem that they had
but the main thing that it did was
demonstrated that hey this is possible
within this ecosystem and that was
enough for him to get leverage to get
operations to start taking him seriously
when he started talking about actually
doing this much more broadly so that's
part of this idea of if you can show
them that it is possible you have a much
easier time getting some sort of
transformation like that to take hold
and actually spread yes I so you've also
discussed how to build engineering and
DevOps practices to support continuous
change in delivery what advice do you
have for us around this I think it's
just an awareness that operations is
really part of building software it's
it's a giant feedback loop operations is
not something that can be done at the
very end because if a service pack comes
out from the operating system make some
of your code break operations doesn't
fix that
development fixes that so that's the
definition of a feedback loop so
the tighter you can make that feedback
the less money and time you waste here's
what I mean by that so let's say the
developer introduces some sort of defect
in a traditional kind of siloed
organization the developer introduces
some sort of defect and it makes it
through all the regular testing and the
QA testing and all that stuff and makes
it to production and for some reason it
will not work in the production
ecosystem because of some operational
factor conflicting with a service pack
operating system or clustering latency
or something like that what to fix that
you have to throw that faulty code away
and start over from the beginning so
what that means is you carried that
flawed code through some very expensive
processes you spent a lot of time and
money on that code only to throw it away
and start over and so part of this
motivation for getting operations much
more aligned with development its speed
up that feedback loop because if the
development team now has a deployment
pipeline when they check in code it
tries to deploy that code onto a
realistic production like system you can
find out very early on that hey this is
not going to work because of reasons XY
and Z and you spend a lot less time
carrying that flawed code so it's it's
more it's more and it's about
engineering efficiency but it's also
about cost savings and you know carrying
broken artifacts a lot less time and
speeding up that feedback loop to find
defects and things are not working
correctly together so refactoring or
keeping technical debt levels low often
goes unseen in it's only the con changes
that care enough to take the initiative
to do it how do you as an architect look
for these attributes of excellence and
individual team members and then
training others such as product owners
and managers to understand and recognize
these attributes and team members well I
think one of the things that's important
to do is don't put roadblocks in front
of people to discourage them from doing
stuff you want them to do a great
example of that is expecting your
developers to refactor aggressively but
then also force them to use feature
branches and conversion control because
those two things are contrary to one
another because if you're living on a
feature branch some
and you find some flaw in the code that
needs to be refactored you're gonna get
punished hard for doing that just in
terms of the merge conflict you're going
to generate because you're living on a
feature branch and so what that does is
discourage developers from doing it
because they have to go an extraordinary
long way out of their way to do the
right thing versus using something like
feature toggles feature toggles you're
still doing trunk based development but
changes are still isolated from one
another inside those feature toggles but
you're getting continuous integration so
you find out right away when two
developers have bumped into one another
because of a merge conflict or something
like that that's a great example of
something that first of all getting out
of the way of the kind of things you
want people to do and make it so that
they can reasonably do that kind of
stuff
the other thing I think is just have
awareness on the project because it's
something that needs to be done so a lot
of our tech leads keep a kind of a
technical debt backlog that's
independent of the product backlog and
they use time either reserve time and
each iteration or use spare time to kind
of attack that technical debt backlog
you know technical debts what are those
just realities of software and it's not
that you often it's not even that you've
done something wrong the problem is the
entire to software development ecosystem
is in constant motion and sometimes it
changes out from underneath you and
makes decisions that used to be correct
incorrect all of a sudden so that's a
lot of times technical debt is just the
inadvertent normal flow of the software
development ecosystem so I think it's an
important bit of hygiene for projects to
always have some sort of background
restructuring and refactoring exercise
going on to clean up old assumptions or
things that have legitimately changed in
the last while because you're never
going to get software right the
beautiful thing about software is it's
really soft and so if you do it
correctly you can keep a codebase alive
and healthy for very long periods of
time now we have several code bases then
within footworks
that are more than a decade old and
they're pretty clean because
have been diligent effort throughout the
life of that codebase to pay attention
to that stuff give what I often find
though is it I'm within a team you've
got your code monkeys which are pumping
up the features fast but they're also
making a mess and then you've got your
other developers which actually take a
little bit longer to do things but
actually do things right and they are
basically tidy up the technical debt as
they go often product owners and
managers see the code monkey as being
the hero and the actual professional
developer that's writing a good solid
code but he's a little bit slower as
being I guess the saw point of the team
so how do you actually go about I guess
making the managers and pro managers and
product owners realize that that just
shows they're tracking the wrong thing
they're looking at typing speed as a
productivity indicator but it's not
because this is not a purely mechanical
kind of work this is a thought based
creative kind of work so sometimes being
slower and more creative it actually has
more value so I think this is really
about the way that managers perceive
value so I would I would take go out of
my way to highlight something that one
of the slower coders has done to in
greatly improve the code base for
everybody else the other thing I would
say do of course I think this is a great
idea anyway is is pair them up pair the
lightning guys with the slower guys and
try to get some of each of those
characteristics into both of them that
may just mean you get could create a
thunderstorm which would be bad because
not everybody can pair with everybody
else but you know that would definitely
be a way to try to slow down the fast
ones and make them more deliberate but
you know also try to speed up the more
deliberate ones hopefully not in a
different so really this is a really
good idea in terms of empowering
developers what are some of the most
effective ways you found to do this so
one of the things that we've discovered
about developers is that the things that
most companies really focus on things
like salaries and perks and that kind of
stuff our metaphor with that is oxygen
if you don't have enough you're in
trouble but once you hit a certain level
that becomes less important money and
other sorts of perks and other sorts of
job characteristics start rising
importance and one of those is autonomy
developers being creative kinds of
people like autonomy and the ability to
make decisions about things and so
giving people more control over their
world actually helps them I think be
appreciated more because they have more
responsibilities and therefore they get
more credit for what they do and you see
a lot of companies go toward more of a
product based rather than project based
team structure where the product kind of
encapsulate that idea of you know
there's a group of people working
together to create some sort of unified
thing versus just you know one project
right after another yeah you can see
with the autonomy I mean a knife for
myself it's been I'm great but then it's
kind of like you've got to watch the
developers that are looking for the
meter work as well as you put it yeah
absolutely that's always something I
think the architect can take lead has to
keep a close eye on that because it
happens all the time
and I could I would almost contend that
you could go to virtually any software
project and find some over-engineered
stuff and not even maliciously
over-engineer just you know oh we're
building your future proofing here or
you know we thought we'd try this here
and you know just very casually but you
know it is in the nature of software
developers to solve puzzles so we looked
for puzzles to solve everywhere so what
are some of the techniques and creating
high-performing teams that also keep
levels of technical debt manageable
levels if I knew that I'd be rolling
around in big fat stacks of cash like
Scrooge McDuck
I mean its Martin Fowler actually
famously wrote at one point about it's
really hard to measure productivity when
how do you even measure that a software
developer or so you know creating highly
productive teams step one is figure out
a way to measure productivity I mean you
you it's you know it's one of those
things you know it when you see it
you've seen hyper productive teams it's
like you can marvel at it it's like wow
look at how much they are able to do
that's laundered people but it's a
really hard thing to measure in any
quantitative way because there are lots
and lots of different variables and you
know system it's a messy thing I don't I
think there are still lots and lots and
lots of
things that we have to discover about
the engineering discipline of writing
software and it's just such a young
science that we just haven't figured out
some really fundamental things yet
that's a bit like scrum
I mean scrum is great it allowing teams
to move fast in it but it doesn't do a
lot for dealing with technical theater
in that sort of thing so you've actually
got to add other steps and processes on
top of it rich icky the creator of
closure has a great video called simple
made easy and he talks about the
distinction between simple and easy
which is a really important distinction
he makes fun of scrum because every
software project is a marathon but he
said so what scrum did was just say okay
we're gonna take this marathon and turn
it into like a hundred hundred meter
sprints and so every week we're gonna
fire the gun again and get you to sprint
for 100 meters but you can't sprint a
marathon at some point you've got to
take a step back and think about
restructuring and refactoring and
looking at the larger picture of that
stuff and maybe do something that seems
like you know it's not relentlessly
moving forward but sometimes moving
forward is not always the absolute
correct thing to do you've ridden on
building a technology Raider
can you talk a bit about that but what
the babble is and the dangers of living
inside it and how to avoid it and how to
build and maintain that technology rater
well that's new this thing that we
produce that don't works a couple of
times a year in fact we just did a
face-to-face meeting it produces another
radar which will eventually be the March
2017 version of the thoughts radar I
think it's a super valuable document for
us internally because what we're really
doing is because we're all over the
world now I thought work standpoint
we're in 18 or 19 different countries
now around the world and we have lots of
different software projects going on all
over the place and so getting a kind of
consensus of what what's really working
well across the world and what's not
working well that's a really rare kind
of Brett thing to be able to find and
our advantage of course is we're a
consulting company so we have lots of
different projects going on sometimes we
pick the tech stack but sometimes we're
working within the tech stack of an
existing company which gives us a kind
of unique perspective and so the radar
is really us taking advantage of this
unique perspective that we have both
across the world and across a large
number projects to see well how well
does this thing work and how well does
this not work first intended usage so I
think this is a good tool to help people
kind of get out of their own kind of
private technology bubble because you
don't really get a chance to assess a
lot of brand-new technologies when
you're working on a long-term project
and so getting to dip your toe into kind
of what's interesting and you I think is
not a bad way to keep track of what's
happening in interesting the world and
just about all technology projects or
should I say technical projects I've
been part of the biggest problems are
just about always and never technology
base but rather people based why is this
and what tips do you have on our fixing
the people problems well so this goes
back to the history lesson stuff we were
talking about before a Gerald Weinberg
to give this out in the 1970s in his
book secrets of consultant I believe it
was that book where he said it's always
a people problem no matter what it looks
like it's always a people problem and
that's the fundamental problem in
software is it's always a people problem
we've known that for a long time we
still haven't figured out a way to get
around that I think it's one of those
things where we take two steps forward
and one step back so we keep figuring
stuff out so I think you know back when
I boys first joined thought works 12
years ago agile was still a kind of a
fraught conversation with a lot of
organizations who you know weren't sure
is that were that kind of hippie stuff
was gonna work and you know you had to
do a lot of selling on that idea but
over the last few years we figured out
where it works well and places where it
doesn't work as well and so we have a
pretty good set of engineering practices
around those ideas now and I think
that's you know that's the the way that
we continue to move forward is you know
two steps forward one step back learn
some new stuff and then learn these
implications of that new stuff and you
keep rinsing and repeating now you've
talked about avoiding yesterday's best
practice from becoming tomorrow's
anti-pattern so what does an
anti-pattern and how do we do this
the name of my keynotes is why does
yesterday's best practice become
tomorrow's anti-pattern and and
anti-pattern is of course taken from the
the pattern movement but most people
misinterpret anti-pattern just as a
synonym for bad but you don't need an T
pattern being bad because we already
have a word for bad we have the word bad
what an T pattern really means is
something that initially looks like a
good idea but then turns out to have
been a terrible idea after the fact and
and we have a lot of those things in
software but part of the problem is one
that I talked about earlier is this
constantly shifting ecosystem that we're
dealing with in software so this is
something that we're talking about in
the evolutionary architecture book
because how do you build an architecture
that evolves and can actually
accommodate all this change so here's
the kind of a thought experiment that
we're pitching to people so take a
computer and it's all an operating
system and maybe an application server
and a bunch of libraries other stuff on
it and then unplug it from the wall and
stick it in a closet for a year at the
end of the year take it out of the
closet plug it back into the wall plug
it back into the internet and what's the
first thing it's going to want to do 57
updates available because even though
you didn't change a single byte on that
computer the entire world kept shifting
and changing and around it and this is
one of the fundamental problems we have
in software is even a perfect decision
today may be invalidated by the software
development ecosystem tomorrow because
the entire thing shifts in a way that we
could never have anticipated and so
that's why we're actually spending a lot
of time and effort in thinking about
this idea of evolutionary architecture
can you and evolve ability as one of
those first-class ill-at-ease in
software architecture and what would it
look like to build an architecture that
can withstand these kind of unexpected
changes that seem to pop up all the time
we refer to this as the Donald Rumsfeld
problem which is probably less known
outside the US our former defense
secretary Donald Rumsfeld very famously
at one point made the distinction
between known unknowns and unknown
and the the real terror in software
architecture the unknown unknowns
because you know about known unknowns
okay I need to add geolocation to this
project and I don't know anything about
that but I know that it exists and I
know the resources for it it's the
unknown unknowns like we have this weird
concurrency bug and we can't figure out
how to solve it those are all the things
that end up nabbing and software so what
does fine you looked like is an
architect and how do you deal with it
well I think failure comes in a couple
of flavors one is Miss assessing the
problem to begin with and choosing the
wrong architecture that doesn't support
the kind of things as you want this is
also known as resume driven development
or chasing the next shiny thing from an
architecture standpoint now chasing the
next shiny things with architectural
standpoint that's a great way to learn
new stuff probably not a good way to
build effective software the other thing
that happens that degrades architecture
is that you choose an architectural
pattern for a perfectly good reason but
then people start degrading it for their
own reasons so let me give you a classic
example of this so as the architect you
choose a traditional layered
architecture that isolates persistence
and business rules and presentation in
individual layers from one another but
then the reporting team comes to you and
says ok look going through all those
layers is just too slow we need access
from the presentation tier directly to
the database now as the architect you
can let that happen and say ok well
performance is why we had to do that but
now you've thrown away the entire reason
you chose that layered architecture to
begin with because the reason you chose
a layered architecture at least one of
the reasons is layers of isolation so
you can easily make changes to the
persistence library for example without
affecting anything else but now you've
gone and coupled the top layer to the
bottom layer which means that you can't
make changes anywhere through those
layers without breaking everything so
that's a good example of choosing the
correct architectural pattern but then
not policing it as people use it and
into letting it degrade over time
because of negligence if you could go
back in time and change the way you
progressed through your career what
would you change
I had no earthly idea because I didn't
have any sort of firm concrete plan to
begin with and so trying to go back and
reverse engineer that fix it would
probably just lead me to a terrible
place
I was very explicitly told when I was in
university that the only real career
path in computers was to learn mainframe
assembly language and I decided to not
take that advice which turned out to be
a really good thing so I've been really
fortunate in that I've been able to I've
worked on lots and lots of different
software projects I've been a consultant
for a really long time and so I've seen
a lot of a lot of software projects that
a lot of different kinds of things and
so I try to leverage my knowledge of
history and how things fit together kind
of put a filter on the the new world for
example I'll give you a great example of
that the micro services ecosystem they
are very slowly reimplemented all of the
corbett named services CEO Corbeau is
this ancient kind of integration
technology back in the 80's and 90's and
they did a lot of distributed computing
stuff so much so that they created a
bunch of different categories for
coordinate services I think there were
eight of them
naming transaction support service
discovery resiliency and we're slowly
reimplemented micro service ecosystem so
I can tell you what the near-term future
of micro service is going to be we're
going to finish implementing the rest of
those korba services because they needed
those facilities for distributed
computing then and we need a different
flavor of those services for distributed
computing now so that's one of the
advantages of having some sort of
breadth and history because these
patterns do keep repeating themselves we
keep solving the same problem over and
over in slightly different nuanced ways
so that's one of the best things about
my career is the fact that I've been a
consultant and have been able to look at
a lot of different projects the other
thing is so you mentioned one of my
titles the self-proclaimed title from
Thor works meme Wrangler which comes
from the the Dawkins definition of a
meme as a viral unit of thought and
wrangle of course is to kind of herd or
settle to speed
and for argument's once I kind of chose
that title tongue-in-cheek from a
thought work standpoint it became sort
of self-fulfilling prophecy because now
I'm actively looking for means of things
across the software development
ecosystem so metal work is more
interesting that work is one I mean so
as architectures abstract until it's
operationalize so I'm now sort of a
self-fulfilling prophecy now trying to
find those kind of meta patterns within
the software develop an ecosystem and
talk about them and things like talks
and keynotes so what advice do you have
for software engineers thinking about
making the transition toward architect
based roles and what do they need to be
aware of before moving in that direction
the first thing I would do is take a
serious look at your soft skills
particularly things like writing and
speaking and that kind of stuff because
that's the thing that's gonna blindside
you as you move in the architect role I
would see if you can pair with an
existing architect before you make a big
leap just to see if you like that job
there's a lot of developers get to
become architects and they hate it
because it's all meetings and it's all
settled in disputes and everybody has
important stuff they care about you know
they don't care about the other people's
important stuff and so a lot of
technical people will find that they
don't like that leadership aspect of
architecture so if you can find a way to
sample it to try it before you buy it
I think that would be great if you could
pair with an existing architect for a
day or two just to kind of get a feel
for the job I think that's a good idea
and you know start looking at things
like architectural patterns books and
some of the technical stuff around
architecture and see if you really like
that I find that one of the things that
appeals to me about architecture is the
kind of you know piecing together
systems that that really react the way
that you want them to in terms of all
these architectural characteristics
you've identified I think that's a
really interesting challenge and it
doesn't have to turn into metal work so
if somebody really likes that kind of
intellectual challenge then it's a
perfect fit but it's hard to know if you
like that until you've actually tried it
yeah yeah I know for myself that it's
it's really hard to basically move from
engineering to architecture and back and
forth and I mean oh I'll spend some time
on that and
architectural role and then get really
frustrated because because either I'm
losing my technical skills or it just
feels like I'm just too far removed from
everything and then vice versa as well
when I'm actually spending time I'm a
deeply technical stuff I feel that I
need to get up I need to step right back
and see what's going on across the
broader picture do you find that as well
well I think that's I think that's a
challenge that every architect has to
solve for their own organization is you
know how much technical stuff can they
carve out how much technical stuff
should they carve out wonder the problem
a lot of brand-new architects have is
they try to micromanage every single
decision on projects you should give
that up
you should let tech leads make decisions
so you pick the architectural style let
them pick the details and how to
implement that architectural style
because you're what you're doing is
allowing them enough context or
gradually growing to be an architect as
well so that's another pitfall is
micromanaging all these decisions
because now you have the power to tell
people which framework to use I'm going
to tell up now sometimes you're better
off letting them choose for themselves
yeah what if we don't discuss that we
really should have we've talked about a
lot of stuff so one of the things I
think is really critical to becoming a
really successful architect is learning
how to present your ideas really well
using tools like keynote or PowerPoint
or the slide stuff in Google that turns
out to be a really critical skill
because you've got to sell these ideas
to management you've got to provide
detailed technical things to sell these
ideas to developers so if there's one
kind of soft skill that you've never had
any instruction end it's probably doing
presentations both from putting slides
together an effective way to just the
mechanics of actually presenting in
front of group of people the more
practice you can get for that the better
off you are because it's definitely
something that gets better with practice
so we've asked can people find out more
about now what you do new so I'm on
twitter my twitter handle is in e al the
number for D which is pronounced Neil
Ford so it's the leet speak version of
name my website is Neil afford comm but
it's Neil with an A not an I so it's any
al-awadi comm and the evolutionary
architecture website is where you can
find out stuff about the book that's
coming up I'm work for thought works so
that's what works comm which is a very
interesting place that is always hiring
passionate developers and I'm also
co-chairing the to Riley software
architecture conferences one in New York
coming up in April and the other one in
London this year coming up in October we
had great events in New York in October
last year and expect to have great
events again this year including
something that I think is absolutely
unique in the conference space which is
build it we have a party game called
architectural Coty's which a lot of
people do now take these little problems
and build architectures for them we're
doing it as a conference wide party game
with drinks and pizza and judges and
prizes and all that sort of stuff so we
have figured out a way to get architects
to network and do work under the guise
of having fun at a conference and last
time we did this we were having a hard
time getting them to go get drinks
because they were so caught up in the
little architectures they were designing
so it turned out to be a great fun thing
so we're gonna do that again in New York
and now London because it's a great way
to network but it's also a great way to
play around with you know designing
architectures with Dierks what could be
wrong with that yeah it sounds good so
Neil thanks for joining us today my
pleasure thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at Etsy -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at se
radio.com
you can also email us a team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening